{"tossups": [{"question": "This document called for reform of the Democratic Party beginning in the South and rallied for universities to change because they are in a \u201cpermanent position of social influence\u201d. This document notes that the two ills of society are nuclear weapons, \u201csymbolized by the bomb\u201d and the \u201cSouthern struggle against racial bigotry\u201d. It was completed at a UAW retreat, though later, the organization that commissioned this work shifted support to SNCC. Tom Hayden wrote, for ten points, what 1962 Students for Democratic Society manifesto?", "answer": "<b> Port Huron Statement</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1686, the Marquis de Denonville tricked and seized 50 Iroquois chiefs, who were sent to Marseille to become these people. One infamous site to hold these people was the Bagne of Toulon, where Jean Valjean was sentenced in<em> Les Miserables</em> to be one of these people. Miguel de Cervantes was kept for five years in Algiers as one of these people, 12,000 of whom were freed at the Battle of Lepanto. Criminals and prisoners of war were often condemned to be, for ten points, what type of laborer who rowed Mediterranean warships?", "answer": "<b> galley slaves</b> (prompt on a partial answer)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A legend about this site holds that it was created from two boys that turned into boulders after a day of playing in the rain. Bob Hawke falsely promised the Mutitjulu community that this site would not be disturbed. In order to preserve a \u201cDreamtime Track\u201d, the nearby Anangu tribe asks visitors not to climb this site. This site is alternatively known as Ayers Rock and is held sacred by the nearby Aboriginese. For ten points, identify this large sandstone formation in the Northern Territory of Australia.", "answer": "<b> Uluru</b> (accept<b> Ayers Rock</b> before mention)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This man was once approached by a disguised Mircea the Elder, who asked him for peace talks just prior to a disaster at Rovine. The Ulu Cami mosque of Bursa was built by this man to commemorate his victory over Western Europe during the Crusade of Nicopolis. This man allegedly died by banging his head on a cage after he was captured near the city of Cubuk following his defeat at the Battle of Ankara to Tamerlane. For ten points, identify this son of Murad I, an Ottoman sultan named for the speed of his military victories.", "answer": "<b> Bayezid the Thunderbolt</b> (accept<b> Bayezid I</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s work<em> The Compedium of Revelations</em> was sent to one pope after he declined to join his Holy League against one invader. This man\u2019s prophecy of a \u201cCyrus of the North\u201d came true when Charles VIII invaded Italy. In order to cleanse his city of sin, this man organized an event where Boccaccio\u2019s art was burned in the Bonfire of the Vanities. This man came to power after his city ousted the Medici family in 1494. For ten points, identify this Dominican friar who briefly controlled Florence.", "answer": "Girolamo<b> Savonarola</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The HEAR Act was passed to facilitate this process and was used on two drawings by Egon Schiele. The 1998 Washington Principles set guidelines for this legal process. A 2018 report issued by B\u00b4en`edicte Savoy and Felwine Sarr recommended over 70,000 objects in the Mus\u00b4ee du Quai Branly undergo this process. Hungary and Poland have been criticized for failing in this process with Jewish-owned artwork confiscated by the Nazis. For ten points, name this process where the rightful owners or their descendants can reclaim stolen artwork.", "answer": "art<b> restitution</b> (accept<b> returning</b> stolen<b> art</b>, accept<b> returning art</b> that the Nazis stole from Jews before \u201cB\u00b4en`edicte Savoy,\u201d accept obvious equivalents)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One theoretician in this sect was Attar of Nishapur, who wrote<em> The Conference of the Birds</em>. Shamil of the Caucasian Imamate was a member of this sect, which includes the Bektashi Order, many of whom are Bosnians. Psychological commentaries made by members of this sect discuss the Nafs, Qalb and Ruh. Schools of this sect include the Naqshbandi and the Senussi, and people in this sect undergo Muraqabah meditation. Schools in this sect include tariqas. People in this sect seek ihsan, or perfection of worship of Allah. For ten points, name this mystic Islamic sect.", "answer": "<b> Sufi</b>sm (accept<b> Tasawwuf</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Lucullus McWhorter documented a losing warrior in this war in his<em> Yellow Wolf</em>. One side\u2019s attempted violation of the Treaty of Walla Walla sparked this conflict, in which Poker Joe and Toohoolhoolzote were killed. After fleeing to the Bitterroot Mountains, one side in this war was surprised in an attack at the Big Hole. Arthur Chapman translated the losing commander in this war\u2019s surrender speech, in which he proclaimed that \u201cI will no longer fight\u201d. Looking Glass and Chief Joseph were leaders of the namesake tribe in, for ten points, what 1877 conflict?", "answer": "<b> Nez Perce</b> War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The first one of these devices was made from strips of gold attached to a plastic triangle. A group of PhD students that left to form Fairchild, which manufactured these devices, were known as the \u201ctraitorous eight\u201d. That group split from a company whose founder developed these devices with John Bardeen and Walter Brittain. William Shockley is credited with developing these things. Created to replace vacuum tubes, for ten points, what semiconductor devices amplify current or act as switches?", "answer": "<b> transistor</b>s", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "This state\u2019s navy won the Battle of Ostia against marauding Saracens. Land in this state was the subject of the<em> Diploma Ottonianum</em>, which confirmed the Donation of Pepin. This state historically included the enclaves at Pontecorvo and the Comtat Venaissin as well as land in Emilio-Romagna. On the 20th of September, 1870, the Bersaglieri defeated a force of volunteer Zouaves and Swiss Guards, ending this state\u2019s existence. For ten points, name this stare ruled by the Pope, a predecessor to the Vatican City.", "answer": "<b> Papal</b> States (or<b> State of the Church</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Rufus Dawes took command of the Iron Brigade\u2019s 6th Wisconsin Regiment during this battle in which he repeatedly clashed with enemy forces at the Hagerstown turnpike. The winning side of this battle used whiskey to persuade the 51st Pennsylvanian Regiment to capture a key objective. After noticing troops crossing Snavely\u2019s Ford, Robert Toombs withdrew from a bridge in this battle that was then seized by Ambrose Burnside. The Emancipation Proclamation was issued after, for ten points, what 1862 battle in Maryland, the bloodiest single day in US history?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Antietam</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Baron von Grimm wrote a parable about a young Bohemian\u2019s adventures to Paris to see the desolate state of this art form. A 1755 essay by Francesco Algarotti on this art form influenced the back to basics approach on this form championed by Christoph Gluck. The first work in this form is considered to be Jacopo Peri\u2019s<em> Dafne</em>. Many of Mozart\u2019s works in this form are classified as Singspiel, such as his<em> The</em> <em>Abduction from the Seraglio</em>. For ten points, name this art form of works such as Bizet\u2019s<em> Carmen</em>.", "answer": "<b> opera</b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This man split with a prominent supporter after that supporter\u2019s conviction in the \u201cBread and Roses\u201dstrike in Lawrence, Massachusetts. This man disagreed with Victor Berger regarding the \u201csewer\u201d tactics promulgated by his supporters. This man was arrested in Canton for opposing the draft and delivered a two-hour speech in his defense. Charles Ruthenberg led a May Day protest in Cleveland against this man\u2019s imprisonment. For ten points, name this five-time Socialist Party candidate tried under the Espionage Act in 1917.", "answer": "Eugene V.<b> Debs</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A recent viral photo taken in this country shows Alaa Salah dressed in white and gesturing while standing on top of a car. Awad ibn Auf resigned after heading this country\u2019s transitional government for one day. Despite backing from Egypt and Saudi Arabia, the director of this country\u2019s National Intelligence and Security Service, Salah Gosh, also resigned due to allegations of war crimes in Darfur. For ten points, name this country, where protesters recently ousted Omar al-Bashir in Khartoum.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Sudan</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>An actor most famous for his work with this group appeared as Vyacheslav Molotov in the 2017 film</b><em><b> The Death of Stalin</b></em><b>. That man played the family man-slash-torturer Jack Lint in the dystopian film</b><em><b> Brazil</b></em><b>, which was directed and written by another member of</b> <b>this group. Cupid\u2019s foot from (+)</b> <b>Bronzino\u2019s</b><em><b> Venus, Cupid, Folly, and Time</b></em><b> is used to</b> <b>crush the title of this group\u2019s program, which aired three and a half seasons on the BBC. (*)</b> Terry Gilliam, Michael Palin, and Graham Chapman, who portrayed King Arthur searching for the Holy Grail, are three of the six members of, for ten points, what legendary British comedy troupe that produced a \u201cFlying Circus\u201d TV show?", "answer": "<b> Monty Python</b> (accept the<b> Python</b>s; accept<b> Monty Python\u2019s Flying Circus</b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>Fernando la Madrid tried to spark an uprising in this city by leading the Cavite mutiny. Limahong\u2019s attack on this city prompted Miguel de Legazpi to resettle this city\u2019s Chinese</b> <b>residents. The University of (+)</b> <b>Santos Tomas was converted to an internment camp</b> <b>during the Japanese occupation of this city. Members of the Katipunan staged the Cry of Balintawak in this city, which instigated an armed independence movement led by Andres (*)</b> Bonifacio. Spanish galleons travelling between Acapulco and this city brought an influx of New World silver to Asia. For ten points, name this capital city of the Philippines.", "answer": "<b> Manila</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Gaining power via Julia Maesa, the successor to this man fought the Battle of Nisibis against the Parthians and lost power at the Battle of Antioch. Artabanus V refused a marriage proposal by this man, who was murdered while (+) urinating by Justin Martialis. This man slaughtered Alexandrians for mocking the circumstances of his brother\u2019s death. Succeeded by (*) </b> Macrinus, this ruler declared all free men Roman citizens in the<em> Constitutio</em> <em>Antoniniana</em>. This son of Septimius Severus killed his brother Geta. For ten points, name this Emperor who created his namesake bathhouse in Rome.", "answer": "<b> Caracalla</b> (accept<b> Antoninus</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Members of this group\u2019s May 19th Coalition helped commit the 1981 Brink\u2019s robbery which resulted in the death of Nyack\u2019s first black police officer. This group operated out</b> <b>of a ballroom with a dried blood strain from a shooting and was called the (+)</b> <b>Flint War</b> <b>Council. LSD advocate Timothy Leary was broken out of prison by this group that had earlier bombed a women\u2019s bathroom in the (*) </b> Pentagon after an American bombing raid on Hanoi. The Days of Rage were conducted by, for ten points, what left wing terrorist organization that declared a state of war against the United States in 1970?", "answer": "<b> Weather Underground</b> Organization (accept<b> Weathermen</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man argued that long-time incarceration was the most severe, but also most</b> <b>humane, punishment, in a campaign that resulted in the establishment of Walnut</b> <b>Street Prison. A feud with William (+)</b> <b>Shippen caused this man to resign from</b> <b>one position after he accused Shippen of misappropriating food and wine meant for</b> <b>soldiers. This man promoted \u201cdepletion\u201d as a method for treating (*)</b> disease including during a 1793 Yellow Fever outbreak in Philadelphia. For ten points, name this Pennsylvanian physician who served as Surgeon General of the Continental Army.", "answer": "Benjamin<b> Rush</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}